ALEXIS MARCHAND

address DPMMS, Centre for Mathematical Sciences, Wilberforce Road, Cambridge CB3 oWB (UK)

email aptm3@cam.ac.uk

website dpmms.cam.ac.uk/~aptm3

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research is in *geometric group theory*, a field concerned with understanding groups — algebraic structures encoding the symmetries of mathematical objects — by studying their actions on geometric spaces. I am particularly interested in understanding connections between group-theoretical structure and *non-positive curvature*.

Keywords: stable commutator length, bounded cohomology, quasimorphisms, topology of surfaces, hyperbolicity, CAT(0) cube complexes, group rings, free group automorphisms.

EMPLOYMENT

²⁰²⁴⁻²⁵ JSPS Postdoctoral Fellow for Research in Japan · Kyoto University

Mentor: Koji Fujiwara

EDUCATION

2021-24 Ph.D. in Pure Mathematics · *University of Cambridge*

Thesis: Computations and lower bounds for scl and the relative Gromov seminorm Supervisor: Henry Wilton

2017-21 Dipl. ENS · École Normale Supérieure de Lyon

2020-21 M.Sc. in Mathematics · Université Grenoble Alpes

Mention Très Bien

Thesis: Automorphismes extérieurs de produits libres : revêtements abéliens caractéristiques et

représentations libres

Supervisor: François Dahmani

2019-20 M.A.St. in Mathematics · *University of Cambridge*

Pass with Merit

Essay: Rigidity Theorems for Hyperbolic Groups

Supervisor: Henry Wilton

2017-19 B.Sc. in Mathematics · École Normale Supérieure de Lyon

Research internships:

- Topology of complex affine varieties, with Hossein Movasati in IMPA, Rio de Janeiro (2019)
- Geometry of Coxeter groups, with Caterina Campagnolo in KIT, Karlsruhe (2018)

ACCEPTED PAPERS

[1] Alexis Marchand, Bavard duality for the relative Gromov seminorm, 2023. *Enseign. Math.* (to appear). arXiv:2305.02149

- [2] Alexis Marchand, Isometric embeddings of surfaces for scl, 2023. *Groups Geom. Dyn.* (to appear). arXiv:2302.04133
- [3] Alexis Marchand, Free representations of outer automorphism groups of free products via characteristic abelian coverings, *J. Group Theory* **26** (2023), no. 2, 399-420.

DOI:10.1515/jgth-2021-0154 · arXiv:2107.11230

PREPRINTS

[4] Alexis Marchand, From letter-quasimorphisms to angle structures and spectral gaps for scl, 2024. arXiv:2402.13856

EXPOSITORY ARTICLES

- [5] Alexis Marchand, Makers of patterns: from Escher to Coxeter, Eureka 66 (2020).
- [6] Alexis Marchand, Géométrie des groupes et courbure négative, *Journal de Mathématiques des Élèves de l'ENS de Lyon* **IV** (2020).

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2021-24 Undergraduate supervisions · Trinity College & Peterhouse College, Cambridge

- Analysis & Topology (IB) 46 contact hours
- Linear Algebra (IB) 16 contact hours
- Geometry (IB) 34 contact hours
- Riemann Surfaces (II) 31 contact hours

2024 Part III examples classes · *University of Cambridge*

Teaching assistant for Geometric Group Theory — 8 contact hours

2022-23 Admissions interviews · Christ's College, Cambridge

Co-interviewer for undergraduate admissions in mathematics

2021-23 Part III drop-in sessions · *University of Cambridge*

Drop-in session leader for Group Cohomology, Mapping Class Groups

²⁰¹⁹⁻²⁰ School tutoring · Stimulus, Cambridge

Volunteer tutor in mathematics in secondary schools

2018-19 Colles · Lycée Aux Lazaristes, Lyon

Oral examiner in mathematics for first-year students in a preparatory class — 44 contact hours

2017-21 French as a foreign language · ItinérENS, Lyon

Volunteer teacher of French classes for refugees and migrants — more than 100 contact hours

ORGANISATIONAL EXPERIENCE

2023-24 Junior geometry seminar · *University of Cambridge*

Co-organiser of the graduate students' seminar in geometry

2022 Reading seminar · University of Cambridge

Organiser of a reading seminar on generalisations of hyperbolic groups

AWARDS

- 2023 Smith-Knight & Rayleigh-Knight prize · University of Cambridge
 - Grade 3, for the essay Isometric embeddings of surfaces for scl
- 2021 EPSRC PhD studentship · University of Cambridge
 - Three-year studentship funded by the Engineering & Physical Sciences Research Council
- 2017 ENS studentship · École Normale Supérieure de Lyon
 - Four-year studentship with civil servant status funded by the French government

INVITED TALKS

- Nov. 2024 First MMS workshop for young researchers · Kyoto University
- May 2024 Seminari dei baby geometri · Università di Pisa / Scuola Normale Superiore
- Apr. 2024 International young seminar on bounded cohomology & simplicial volume · Online
- Apr. 2024 Geometry and geometric analysis seminar · Purdue University (online)
- Mar. 2024 Geometric group theory seminar · University of Oxford
- Dec. 2023 Bristol junior geometry seminar · University of Bristol
- Jun. 2023 International young seminar on bounded cohomology & simplicial volume · Online
- *Apr.* 2023 Methusalem junior seminar · KU Leuven
- Mar. 2023 Geometry graduate colloquium · ETH Zürich
- Feb. 2023 Junior topology & group theory seminar · University of Oxford
- Feb. 2023 Geometric group theory seminar · University of Cambridge
- Jan. 2023 International young seminar on bounded cohomology & simplicial volume · Online
- Jun. 2022 Séminaire compréhensible · Université Grenoble Alpes
- Apr. 2022 Séminaire des doctorants de St-Charles · Aix-Marseille Université

CONFERENCES ATTENDED

- Apr. 2024 Groups, topology, & applications Gran Bilbao · Euskal Herriko Unibertsitatea
- Mar. 2024 Topological & homological methods in group theory · Universität Bielefeld
- Feb. 2024 GAGTA · CIRM, Marseille
 - Contributed talk & poster
- Jul. 2023 Postgraduate group theory conference · Heriot-Watt University, Edinburgh Contributed talk
- May 2023 Geometry of subgroups · CRM, Montréal
- Jan. 2023 LMS regional meeting · University of Southampton
 - Contributed poster
- Sep. 2022 Recent advances in bounded cohomology · Universität Regensburg
- Jun. 2022 Hyperbolic groups and their generalisations · IHP, Paris
- *Apr.* 2022 Mapping class groups and Out $(F_n) \cdot IHP$, Paris

Apr. 2022 Groups acting on fractals · CIRM, Marseille

Feb. 2022 Workshop on finiteness properties · KIT, Karlsruhe

LANGUAGES

French	Native speaker	Portuguese	Advanced (B2)
English	Fluent (C2). Passed the CAE	Russian	Intermediate (B1)
German	Advanced (B2)	Japanese	Elementary (A2)

July 25, 2024